<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King forasmuch as the Kings Maiestie, in his princely disposition to iustice hauing euer a speciall care and regard to haue repressed the slaughters, spoyles, robberies and other enormities which were so frequent and common vpon the borders of these realmes ...</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21971</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123918</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150688</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33150688</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28709</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21971)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28709)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1874:114)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King forasmuch as the Kings Maiestie, in his princely disposition to iustice hauing euer a speciall care and regard to haue repressed the slaughters, spoyles, robberies and other enormities which were so frequent and common vpon the borders of these realmes ...</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Declaring England and Scotland to be united, and ordering peace along the border.</note>
                  <note>"Giuen under our Signet at our Manour of Greenewich, the nineteenth of May, 1603."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brigands and robbers --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
               <term>Scottish Borders (England and Scotland)</term>
               <term>Welsh Borders (England and Wales)</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28709:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as the Kings Maieſtie, in his Princely diſpoſition to Iuſtice,</hi> hauing euer a ſpeciall care and regard to haue repreſſed the ſlaughters, ſpoyles, robberies, and other enormities which were ſo frequent and common vpon the Borders of theſe Realmes, and to haue reduced and ſettled the ſaid Borders vnto a perfect obedience, to the comfort of his Highneſſe peaceable Subiects: The courſe whereof hath bene heretofore impeded by the difference of the Borders, Engliſh and Scottiſh, till it hath now pleaſed Almighty God, in his great bleſſing to this whole I ſtand, by his Maieſties lawfull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to the Imperiall Crowne of England, not onely to remoue this difference, but alſo to furniſh his Highneſſe with power and force ſufficient to proſecute that his Maieſties Royall and worthy reſolution, as his Highneſſe hath already begunne, entending that the bounds poſſeſt by thoſe rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people, being in fertilitic and all other benefits nothing inferiour to many of the beſt parts of the whole Ile, ſhall be no more the extremities, but the middle, and the Inhabitants thereof reduced to perfect obedience: Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as his Maieſtie is enformed, certaine diſordered and wicked perſons of both Marches, Enemies to Peace, Iuſtice, and quietneſſe, pretending ignorance of his Maieſties reſolution for the vnion of the two Realmes, already ſettled in the hearts of all his good Subiects, and feeding themſelues with a ſmiſter conceit and opinion, that no ſuch vnion ſhould be eſtabliſhed and take effect, ſtill continue in all hinde of robbery and oppreſſion, whereunto they are encouraged by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt and harbour granted vnto them, their wiues, children, goods and geir in the Inland and peaceable parts of both the Realmes, highly to his Maieſties contempt, and fruſtrating of his Highneſſe Commiſſion graunted to the effect aforeſayd.</p>
            <p>And therefore his Maieſtie for the better ſatiſfaction of all his good Subiects, who may ſtand in any doubt of the ſayd Vnion, and to take away all pretence of excuſe from wicked and turbulent perſons, hath hereby thought good to publiſh and make knowen to all thoſe to whoſe knowledge theſe preſents ſhall come, That as his Maieſtie hath found in the hearts of all the beſt diſpoſed Subiects of both the Realmes of all qualities, a moſt earneſt deſire, that the ſayd happy Vnion ſhould bee perfected, the memory of all preterite Diſcontentments aboliſhed, and the Inhabitants of both the Realmes to be the Subiects of one Kingdome: ſo his Highnes will with all conuenient diligence with the aduice of the Eſtates and Parliament of both the Kingdomes make the ſame to be perfited. And in the meane time till the ſayd Vnion be eſtabliſhed with the due ſolemnitie aforeſayd, his Maieſtie doth hereby repute, hold, and eſteeme, and commands all his Highnes Subiects to repute, hold, and eſteeme both the two Realmes as preſently vnited, and as one Realme and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the Subiects of both the Realmes as one people, brethren and members of one body: And in regard thereof, that euery one of them abſtaine and forbeare to commit any kinde of Robbery, Bloodſhed, or any other inſolence or diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or to receiue and harbour the Perſons, Wiues, Children or Goods the Fugitiues and Outlawes of either of the Realmes, but to conteine themſelues inpeace and quietnes, and all ſuch dutifull behauiour as becommeth good and loyall Subiects, certifying all and euery perſon who ſhall doe, practiſe, or attempt any thing to the violating of theſe Preſents, that they ſhall incurre the puniſhment due to the ſayd Rebels, and that the ſame ſhall be executed againſt them with all rigor and extremity to the terror of others.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen vnder our Signet at our Manour of Greenewich, <date>the nineteenth of May 1603.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie. Anno Dom. 1603.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
